Guide to the Emma Goldman Papers, 1909-1941 and undated RL.11353
David M. Rubenstein Rare Book & Manuscript Library
- Letters, 1909-1941 and undated; 1
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Cloud, France) to Tom [Thomas H. Keell] (Stroud, England), [1929] March 21; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman repeats in a postcard his request for special air mail envelopes, then reports that his book will soon be ready.
  - Alexander Berkman (Paris, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1930 January 12; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman writes about the state of the movement in Great Britain and in France. He also discusses possible reviews for his book.
    Anarchism -- Great Britain; Anarchism -- France; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Paris, France) to T.H.K. [Thomas H. Keell] (Stroud, England), 1930 January 30; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In a postcard, Berkman thanks Keell for sending out review copies and wonders if books can be offered for sale.
  - Alexander Berkman (Anvers, Belgium.) to H.K. [Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1930 May 9; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman announces that he has been suddenly expelled from France, but that friends are attempting to get him back into the country. The news is confidential. He comments on attacks made on Keell in the new Freedom journal.
    Deportation -- France -- History -- 20th century; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Tropez, France) to Thomas [Thomas H. Keell] (Stroud, England), 1930 December 2; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    In a postcard, Berkman sends appreciation for being remembered by his friends.
  - Alexander Berkman (Nice, France) to Comrade [Thomas H. Keell] (Stroud, England), 1934 March 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman requests a copy of a pamphlet be mailed to him.
  - Alexander Berkman (Nice, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (Stroud, England), 1934 April 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman comments on the state of the anarchist movement. "...Now would seem to be a most favorable time to spread our ideas.... E. G. [Emma Goldman] writes me from the U.S. that she finds there a very vital interest in our ideas.... On the other hand Fascism seems to be growing everywhere."
  - Alexander Berkman (St. Tropez, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1934 October 31; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman discusses his case for residency in France, and his possible deportation.
    Deportation -- France -- History -- 20th century; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Alexander Berkman (Paris, France) to [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), [193?] December 18; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Berkman comments on the state of the movement: "There seems very little life.... Our people are indifferent and inactive. Sometimes it makes me feel very depressed." He then mentions the possibility of a Russian translation of his Prison Memoirs, and requests two more copies of the book be sent to him.
  - Eugene V. Debs (Terre Haute, Indiana) to W. S. Van Valkenburgh (New York, N.Y.), 1926 January 15; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Debs describes the respect and personal regard he has for Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman, and is at a loss as to why they have been treated so harshly by the United States and Soviet governments.
    Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Van Valkenburgh, Warren Starr, 1884-1938; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Eugene V. Debs (Terre Haute, Indiana) to W. S. Van Valkenburgh (New York, N.Y.), 1926 January 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 2)
    Debs outlines his differences of opinion with Van Valkenburgh. He doesn't agree that Emma Goldman and Alexander Berkman should have expected the treatment they received by the Soviet government or that anarchists would be silenced under a socialist government.
    Socialism; Debs, Eugene V. (Eugene Victor), 1855-1926; Van Valkenburgh, Warren Starr, 1884-1938; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Emma Goldman (New York) to Comrade (n.p.), 1909 April 13; 4 Leaves; 7 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman sends money for support and explains why she cannot send more. She lectures in New York 3-4 times a week, but says that the U.S.A. is driving her to desperation, mostly through attempts to deprive her of citizenship. She states "It's like being condemned to life long exile." It has forced her to cancel planned trips to England, Scotland, and Australia. She adds that she is more determined than ever to go on until the end. She notes that sales of literature have been poor, and that once they settle accounts, she will send more money.
    Anarchists -- United States; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (New York City) to Mr. Stokes (n.p.), 1909 September 10; 8 Leaves; 16 pages; 25 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman defends herself from Stokes' charge that she is a bully, and warns him not to believe newspaper reports. She outlines her methods for obtaining speaking venues, and the harsh response routinely received from police. She defends her right to free speech, and describes the work of the free speech committee. She tells Stokes that whether he assists with the cause is his own affair.
    Anarchism -- United States; Anarchists -- United States; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (New York City) to Mr. Stokes (n.p.), 1909 September 16; 2 Leaves; 4 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman thanks Stokes for his "kind reply and contribution." She describes her plan to release some of her lectures in pamphlet form, then relates how newspaper coverage is often incorrect in coverage of radicals, stating "It is not to be expected that daily papers will report anything correctly pertaining to the revolutionary movement."
  - Emma Goldman (New York City) to Mr. Stokes (n.p.), 1910 December 20; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman asks Stokes to clarify his subscription to her book.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman to Thos. H. Keell (London, England), 1914 November 24; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that she has been lecturing on the war and "on the Drama" but has gotten great satisfaction about lecturing on the war. She notes Mother Earth's reply to Kropotkin's article on war and capitalism, and her feelings regarding the matter. She announces that Alexander Berkman has been arrested in New York City and is awaiting trial, but is successfully holding meetings in Pittsburgh.
    World War, 1914-1918; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.; Kropotkin, Petr Alekseevich, kniaz, 1842-1921; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Emma Goldman (New York) to Comrade (n.p.), 1915 February 22; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman makes a payment to her account and a contribution to Freedom. She then states "Am so glad you are going to remain on the paper.... I had hoped to get an article from you." She adds that there is 'an awakened interest" in Anarchist thought in the East, and it is hers to address, with Alexander Berkman away. She closes with "Should the English papers have brought any statements said to be made by Berkman, I hop[e] you will contradict them because he has made no statements, they were faked up by the press."
    Anarchism; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (New York) to Comrade (n.p.), 1915 April 23; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that her successful tour means that many of their debts have been paid. She then mentions the arrest of four comrades, and the cases against them. She then outlines Mother Earth's stance on Peter Kropotkin's views. She adds that she will not be ordering any pamphlets, because they have decided to carry less of a load of printed material than in the past.
    Anarchism -- United States; Anarchists -- United States; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Kropotkin, Petr Alekseevich, kniaz, 1842-1921
  - Emma Goldman (New York) to Comrade (n.p.), 1916 April 11; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes of her arrest and the case against her, and her plans not to make birth control the central issue in the case, unlike Margaret Sanger. She asks for more information regarding the current situation in England, and asks about "the old man" [Kropotkin?] and his views. She then relates the situation regarding the arrest of the Magons and Caplan, and how her energies are tapped. by the defense of Caplan.
    Anarchism -- United States; Anarchists -- United States; Birth control -- United States; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Sanger, Margaret, 1879-1966
  - Emma Goldman (Moscow) to Comrade [Thomas H.] Keell (n.p.), 1921 May 29; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 11 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman requests that Keell write news of England and send copies of Freedom.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 January 9; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 35 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes briefly about her imprisonment in Russia and about Communist refusal to criticise the Bolsheviki, but uses the majority of the letter to respond to a letter in Freedom falsely crediting the anarchists with "glorying in having helped counter-revolutionaries or taking credit for that particular bomb."
    Anarchists; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 January 30; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 36 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that she expects to soon be expelled from Sweden but despairs of finding anywhere else in Europe to go. She rejects the misrepresentations of Bolshevik Russia by a writer, Lansbury. She announces that the New York World would like to publish her articles but cannot decide "whether one is to make use of them rather than to have them make use of me." She discusses her traditional methods for publishing her views, via pamphlet, and how it is no longer easy to circulate them. She adds that any interested publisher will have to pay for her writing, including her book.
    New York world (New York, N.Y.: 1881: Daily); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Stockholm, Sweden) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 March 1; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes at length about her stay with Alexander Berkman in Russia, including the conditions and political interpretations surrounding their stay, as well as her lack of desire to respond to Communist critics. She outlines the articles she plans to write regarding those events. She then describes their trouble in getting visas.
    Communism -- Soviet Union; Visas; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Berkman, Alexander, 1870-1936
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 May 2; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that she has obtained a visa to remain in Germany for a month, she hopes longer, but that this does not resolve her visa problem. Either she can go before the United States Supreme Court to discuss her citizenship or she can marry to resolve the problem. She requests feedback regarding her articles published in the World. In a postscript she notes that a friend has been questioned by Scotland Yard as a result of connections with her.
    Visas; New York world (New York, N.Y.: 1881: Daily); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 May 9; 1 Leaves; 3 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman offers to pay to have her articles published in one issue of Freedom, and requests that Keell or [William C.] Owen write a statement of support of her publishing the pieces in the World. She relates the experience of an Chinese anarchist, and outlines the corrupt practices of Hillman and Foster, two Americans recently returned from Russia.
    Anarchists; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Owen, William C.
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 May 14; 4 Leaves; 7 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman supplies details regarding the publication of her articles in Freedom. She defends herself against charges that the American Secret Service supported her stay in Russia. She comments on the lack of Bolshevik sources for her work, as well as on a potential plan for her to marry in order to resolve her visa problems.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Visas; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 May 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman points out a paragraph that was accidentally deleted from one of her articles, and requests its reinsertion.
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), [1922] July 13; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that she has been uncharacteristically out of spirits and unable to write letters, but must now pull herself together in order to write her book on Russia, requested by Harper Bros. She corrects an impression that she intended to marry William C. Owen to resolve her visa issues, and says she has put any such proposal behind her; she hopes to continue her stay in Germany.
    Anarchists; Harper & Brothers; Visas; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Owen, William C.
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 August 3; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman makes plans for a pamphlet, then notes Bertrand Russell's failed attempt to get her a visa for England, despite her plan to remain in Germany. She adds that she has completed 5 chapters of her book, and has sent them to the president of Harper Bros. She outlines the difficulty of her plans to continue writing.
    Harper & Brothers; Visas -- England; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Russell, Bertrand, 1872-1970
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 September 21; 3 Leaves; 3 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman comments on her inability to find people in the United States to put forth her views, on the opposition to her printing her views on Russia in the New York World, and on Bill Haywood. She provides a brief update on the progress of her book, before outlining details regarding the publishing of her pamphlet.
    Anarchism -- United States; New York world (New York, N.Y.: 1881: Daily); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Haywood, Big Bill, 1869-1928
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 October 2; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman discusses her need of typewriter supplies, then requests a copy of a manuscript she sent to Freedom in 1921 regarding arrests in Russia. She notes that she is moving again.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 October 12; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman again discusses typewriter supplies, then makes requests for articles from Freedom.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 October 28; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman discusses her plans to help distribute the pamphlet, and mentions that she is nearing the end of her book and her difficulties judging the merit of her work. She requests publications to be mailed to a student in America.
    Anarchists; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 November 5; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes at length about how to end her book on the Russian revolution, then comments on a man who will be deported from Russia.
    Deportation -- Soviet Union -- 20th century; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1922 December 5; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes with complaints about the cost of publishing her pamphlet and the public announcement that she paid to print it. She then writes about finishing her book.
    Press, Anarchist -- Great Britain; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), [1922]; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 23 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman requests copies of Freedom and an approach to a London publisher regarding books by her and Alexander Berkman on Russia. She notes that prices are high in Stockholm, and that they would get rich quickly if they wrote for the American Press, which they are unwilling to do.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1923 March 2; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman states that she has completed a tribute to Rudolf Rocker in honor of his birthday that she would like to publish in Freedom.
    Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Rocker, Rudolf, 1873-1958
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1923 April 6; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman comments on edits to be made to her article on Rudolf Rocker before it is published, that she has come to terms with the cost of her pamphlet, then on how each of them is now imprisoned in their own country. She despairs about the publication of her book, and closes with comments on the inability of the movement to support the publication of Freedom.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Rocker, Rudolf, 1873-1958
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1924 January 4; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes to arrange a meeting. She notes that their meeting venue might back out because of the possibility of trouble, and that the preliminary report of the Trade Union Mission has disrupted all of the work she had accomplished in London thus far, and points out there will be difficulties in their future work on Russia. She feels discouraged, but "one must go on."
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 Februrary 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 29 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes of the "Bolshevik superstition" that has taken over the anarchist movement, especially in the United States. She adds that "Every day convinces me of the imperative need of a relentless criticism and attack against that gang in Moscow that has poisoned the whole world..." She then reports on the "muddle" that was made of her book, with "13 chapters omitted and the title changed."
    Communism -- Soviet Union; Anarchism -- United States; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 March 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 18 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes regarding articles she has sent or is sending for publication. She adds that a literary agent has accomplished nothing for her thus far.
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 May 10; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that she receives Freedom, "but would like a more personal word" in a letter. She then requests copies of books to be sent to another author.
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 June 12; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman sends a review of a play on the Haymarket riot for possible publication. She addes that her complete book will be published in the Fall. She outlines the attempts made to get her a visa for England. She then notes her sense of gratification that there is growing interest in those imprisoned in Russia.
    Press, Anarchist -- Great Britain; Visas; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 June 28; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 15 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes with alterations to the proofs for her review of the Haymarket riot play. She then condemns an article written by Guy Aldred.
  - Emma Goldman (Berlin, Germany) to Comrade Thomas H. Keell (London, England), 1924 July 16; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes in a postcard that there may be no reply to Aldred's article. She adds that she has obtained a visa from England, and will soon learn the details.
    Visas; Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (Paris, France) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 September 20; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that the printed announcement in Freedom regarding her arrival will more likely bring out members of Scotland Yard to greet her. She had hoped to avoid publicity. She notes the two people that will meet her, and other arrangements made.
    Press, Anarchist -- Great Britain; Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 October 16; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 28 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes that she has been kept busy meeting people and that there are plans to hold a dinner for her. She hopes for a formal meeting next week.
  - Emma Goldman (no place) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 October 17; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes requesting copies of her Essays, and address for various supporters.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 October 22; 1 Leaves; 2 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes regarding procuring copies of her Essays, arrangements for the dinner to be held in her honor, and obtaining literature for people she is meeting.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), [1924] October 31; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 14 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes regarding obtaining the list of names for mailing announcements of the dinner in her honor, and regarding a meeting.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 November 9; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 13 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes regarding writing paper and envelopes she cannot use because the postage is prohibitive.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade [Thomas H. Keell] (n.p.), 1924 November 19; 2 Leaves; 3 pages; 27 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman records the writing assignments she has agreed to take and outlines plans for her to deliver a lecture on Russia. She requests names of Freedom subscribers who might contribute to the rental of the venue.
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940; Keell, Thomas H.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 November 25; 2 Leaves; 2 pages; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman sends a query regarding duties to be paid for publications then requests the subscriber list so that she can send her mailing out.
  - Emma Goldman (London, England) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 December 3; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 33 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes a letter to the subscribers of Freedom, requesting their monetary support for her lectures on Russia. A subscriber has written a note on the letter, requesting clarification as to the writer, since Goldman signed it "E. G. Kershner."
    Freedom (London, England: 1886); Goldman, Emma, 1869-1940
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Comrade (n.p.), 1924 December 5; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 21 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman requests the recipient to attend to the shipment of her Essays, along with a few other details.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1924 December 17; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes requesting publications, and provides details regarding the publishing of her book. She notes that the venue for her lecture has changed, after insurance and other costs made the price of Queen's Hall prohibitive.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Thomas H. Keell (Willesden, England), 1924 December 22; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 9 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman writes a postcard asking Keell to return a manuscript which she wrote badly. She adds that she cannot pay for copies of Berkman's book because she needs them for publishers.
  - Emma Goldman (n.p.) to Tom [Keell] (n.p.), 1924 December 24; 1 Leaves; 1 page; 26 cm (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Goldman asks Keell if they have a contact in Paisley, because the Women's Guild there has asked for the date of her lecture. She then outlines her Christmas gifts for his family, and invites them to tea.